http://www.nurses.ab.ca/home/privacy-policy

Currency of practice
Fitness to practice (FTP)
Verify a nurse
Verify employees (login required)
Request access to employee verification
Practice and learning
Keep up to date with practice standards
Browse our documents on nursing practice standards in Alberta and guidelines that are essential to your scope of practice.
Medical assistance in dying
Responsibilities for distributing Take Home Naloxone Kits and Narcan® Nasal Spray (naloxone)
Practice and learning resources outside of CARNA
Student and Novice Nurse Program (SNNP)
Disciplinary publication framework
Effects of COVID-19 Pandemic on Professional Conduct Processes – 3 April 2020
About
What is CARNA?
What we do
Our vision, mission, and values
Regulatory philosophy
News
What's nursing in Alberta like?
CARNA regions
Our partners
Review of complaints processes and outcomes
Review of approach to fitness to practise
Review of registration process for internationally educated nurses
Last updated: Aug. 10, 2018
For a copy of the complete Personal Information Protection Act Policy including related policies and forms mentioned please contact the privacy officer.
Policy
The College and Association of Registered Nurses of Alberta (CARNA) is committed to maintaining the accuracy, confidentiality and security of the personal information collected from members, applicants, public council representatives and employees.
Accountability
CARNA is committed to protecting all of the personal information that is shared with us. The Personal Information Protection Act (PIPA) is provincial legislation intended to protect the individuals submitting personal information to CARNA. The policies and practices of CARNA have been reviewed to ensure they meet the requirements of this legislation. CARNA has designated one person with the role and responsibilities of a privacy officer. This officer is responsible for CARNA’s compliance with privacy legislation.
Purpose
The primary collection of applicant information is through registration and renewal. This information is used for determining eligibility for registration, as well as to perform other regulatory functions and provide membership benefits through CARNA.Members of CARNA are automatically members of the Canadian Nurses Association (CNA) and their personal contact information is supplied to CNA to confer membership benefits through CNA. By becoming a member of CARNA, the member is consenting to the collection and use of personal contact information for the purpose of providing membership benefits through both CNA and CARNA. The information supplied to CNA will remain confidential to CNA as provided for in CNA’s privacy policy.CARNA shares personal contact information with the Canadian Nurses Protective Society (CNPS) in order to secure professional liability protection for nursing practice for our members.Personal contact information is shared with the Alberta Registered Nurses Educational Trust (ARNET) in order for ARNET to determine eligibility for funding applications.Aggregate information is also provided to Statistics Canada though the Canadian Institute for Health Information as required by Statistics Canada.Personal information may also be collected through other registration member services and may be used in aggregate, non-identifiable form.
Consent
Contact and personal information is not shared with unaffiliated third parties except those we are satisfied are legitimately requesting the information (such as when permitted or required by law).Members and applicants have the option of consenting to release their contact information to third parties that participate in research relevant to nurses, provide information on education and career opportunities, member benefits, specialty practice groups and advisories applicable to the nursing profession. Release of information is subject to approval by CARNA once conditions have been met as outlined in our Access to Information policy (Appendix A of the complete Personal Information Protection Act Policy).Other uses of personal information will be identified either prior to or at the time the information is collected. CARNA will communicate verbally, electronically or in writing the primary purpose of collecting personal information outside of those listed above. Information collected for aggregate use by departments of CARNA is defined in Appendix B of the complete Personal Information Protection Act Policy.
Limit collection
CARNA limits the collection of personal information to those elements we require to meet our obligations. Prospective employee and employee information is collected for the purposes of determining, offering and maintaining employment with CARNA.The Health Professions Act (HPA) and the Registered Nurses Profession Regulation outline the requirements for determining eligibility for registration, which include but are not limited to collecting any information deemed necessary regarding the member or applicant’s fitness to practice, criminal record, employer references and verification of their registration in other jurisdictions. This information is collected by CARNA during the application for initial registration and annual application for renewal of registration.
Disclosure and retention
CARNA shall not use or disclose personal information for purposes other than those identified in this policy unless express consent has been received or the disclosure is otherwise permitted or required by law or legislation.Retention policies have been developed for the organization based on the relevant legislation which includes the HPA, PIPA and requirements from Canada Revenue Agency.
Accuracy
Requests for updates or changes to personal information for members and applicants can be made to the registration department of CARNA.
Sharing and safeguards
All personal information is safeguarded with appropriate security measures and used only for the purposes stated in this policy and only that information which is necessary is released.The HPA includes a number of requirements for regulatory colleges to share and disclose information, which are intended to provide additional transparency and openness from health professions to the public.Public access to informationUnder HPA, when a member of the public asks for information about a regulated member and specifies the member by name, CARNA must provide the following information:the member’s registration number;any conditions imposed on the member’s practice permit;whether the member’s practice permit has been suspended, cancelled or restricted to a specific time frame;the member’s practice specialization recognized by the college;whether or not the member is authorized to provide a restricted activity normally provided by regulated CARNA members; and/orwhether a disciplinary hearing is scheduled to be held or has been heldNotification of conditions on practice permitsIf a member’s practice permit is suspended or cancelled or if conditions are imposed on it, CARNA must notify:the member’s employer(s) (including anyone who employs the member as a consultant, contractor or volunteer);the health authority where the member provides services;the hospital if the member is a member of the hospital's professional staff;the Minister of Health or any organization that administers the payment of fees for the professional services the member provides;another health professional college if the registrar knows that the regulated member is also a member of the other college; andthe governing bodies of any similar profession in other provinces or territories in Canada.If after a review or appeal, a cancellation or suspension is lifted or imposed conditions are varied or removed, CARNA will notify the same parties.Discipline hearingsAll HPA hearings are open to the public unless the hearing tribunal orders otherwise.To obtain the date of a disciplinary hearing, a member of the public may call during business hours, name the regulated member whose hearing they wish to attend and if there is a scheduled date, the information will be provided.To obtain a copy of a decision of a hearing tribunal and/or a transcript of the testimony given before the hearing tribunal, a member of the public must submit a request in writing to CARNA and pay the administration and reproduction costs. The request must be submitted within five years of the date of the disciplinary hearing to which it relates. A record will be kept of the members of the public who receive the information.
Openness
CARNA will share information on the policies and procedures that apply to the management of personal information when requested by any member of the public.
Individual access
An individual may request access to their personal information that CARNA has in its custody and control. Requests must be received in writing and should be forwarded to the attention of the Privacy Officer. A sample form for such requests is found in Appendix C of the complete Personal Information Protection Act Policy. CARNA will attempt to respond to any request within 45 days. CARNA may give an individual access to their personal information. If access is given, a reasonable fee may be charged for the reproduction of the information. However, CARNA may also withhold information according to the provisions of PIPA. If CARNA withholds information, the reasons for denying access will be identified.An individual may challenge the accuracy and completeness of their personal information that CARNA has in its custody and control and may request to have it amended if appropriate.
Challenging compliance
Concerns or complaints regarding CARNA compliance within privacy policy should be directed to:Privacy OfficerCollege and Association of Registered Nurses of Alberta11120 – 178 StreetEdmonton, AB T5S 1P2Tel: (780) 451-0043Fax: (780) 452-3276E-mail: privacy@nurses.ab.caIf dissatisfied with the manner in which the complaint was handled, an individual may contact the following:Office of the Information and Privacy Commissioner of Alberta2460-801 – 6th Avenue SWCalgary, AB T2P 3W2
Home
Connect with usToll Free:1.800.252.9392Tel:780.451.0043Fax:780.452.3276Email:carna@nurses.ab.ca
CARNA officeAddress:11120 178 StreetEdmonton, AlbertaT5S 1P2Office hours:Monday - Friday8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m.
SitemapPrivacy policy
©
College and Association of Registered Nurses of Alberta
